<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Roman Ring</title>
    <link>http://inoryy.com/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Roman Ring</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018--2019</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 24 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://inoryy.com/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>DeepMind, StarCraft II, and The Next Big Thing in AI</title>
      <link>http://inoryy.com/post/deepmind-starcraft2-next-big-thing-ai/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://inoryy.com/post/deepmind-starcraft2-next-big-thing-ai/</guid>
      <description>Couple of days ago out of the blue DeepMind announced a StarCraft II related event, with many of the employees being quite excited about it on twitter. In just a few hours we will see what DeepMind has in store for us, but in the meantime let&amp;rsquo;s take a step back and review how we got here and why it is so important.
Update: the (amazing) event has finished and DeepMind have released a very detailed write-up.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deep Reinforcement Learning with TensorFlow 2.0</title>
      <link>http://inoryy.com/post/tensorflow2-deep-reinforcement-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://inoryy.com/post/tensorflow2-deep-reinforcement-learning/</guid>
      <description>In this tutorial I will showcase the upcoming TensorFlow 2.0 features through the lense of deep reinforcement learning (DRL) by implementing an advantage actor-critic (A2C) agent to solve the classic CartPole-v0 environment. While the goal is to showcase TensorFlow 2.0, I will do my best to make the DRL aspect approachable as well, including a brief overview of the field.
In fact since the main focus of the 2.0 release is making developers’ lives easier, it’s a great time to get into DRL with TensorFlow - our full agent source is under 150 lines!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I Majored in Statistics for a Career in Artificial Intelligence</title>
      <link>http://inoryy.com/post/why-study-statistics-for-artificial-intelligence/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://inoryy.com/post/why-study-statistics-for-artificial-intelligence/</guid>
      <description>Undergraduate major is often the first significant career decision a person makes in his life. As artificial intelligence (AI) becomes more and more ingrained in our society, many people begin to consider a career in AI as a viable choice in their life. However, it is still very rare to have an undergraduate degree fully dedicated to AI, so people opt for what they perceive to be the next best thing - computer science.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>